Guide to the Zora J. Murff photographs, 2013-2015 RL.11686
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Zora J. Murff photographs
2013-2015
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Murff, Zora J.
RL.11686
1.0 Linear Feet 1 box 25 color inkjet prints
Collection comprises twenty-five color inkjet prints from "Corrections," a documentary project by photographer Zora J. Murff. Taken in Iowa, these portraits of male and female teenage offenders on probation, parole, or charged again as adults are further contextualized by images of electronic tracking bracelets, jumpsuits, cells and detention centers, and intake paperwork. Images are accompanied by detailed captions written by the photographer. The prints measure 17 x 22 inches (image size 16 x 20 inches). As a whole, the collection documents the administration and human context of the 21st century juvenile justice system in the U.S. and Iowa. This work received the 2018 ADA Award for Emerging Documentarians. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Arrangement
Prints are arranged in original order as assigned by the photographer.
Biographical Note
Zora J Murff is a Visiting Assistant Professor of Photography at the University of Arkansas. Zora received his MFA in Studio Art from the University of Nebraska–Lincoln and holds a BS in Psychology from Iowa State University. Combining his education in human services and art, Zora's photography focuses on the paradoxical relationship of how images are used to both reinforce and challenge social and cultural constructs. His work has been exhibited nationally, internationally, and featured online including Aperture Magazine, The New Yorker, VICE Magazine, The British Journal of Photography, and The New York Times. In 2018, Zora was selected as a 2019 Light Work Artist-in-Residence, named the Daylight Photo Award Winner in 2017, and was also selected as a LensCulture 2017 Top 50 Emerging Talent with his collaborative partner Rana Young. Zora's first monograph, Corrections, was published by Aint-Bad Editions in 2015 and his second monograph, LOST, Omaha, was published by Kris Graves Projects in 2018.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research. Images may only be used for educational, non-commercial purposes; any other use requires the photographer's permission.
Provenance
The Zora J. Murff photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2018.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
The photographs in this collection were printed on an Epson 7900, using Moab Entrada Rag Bright paper and UltraChrome ink.
Related Materials
Book (see Duke University Libraries catalog): Corrections, Savannah, Georgia: Aint-Bad Editions, 2015.
Content Description
Collection comprises twenty-five color inkjet prints from Corrections, a documentary project by photographer Zora J. Murff. Taken in Iowa, these portraits of male and female teenage offenders on probation, parole, or charged again as adults are further contextualized by images of electronic tracking bracelets, jumpsuits, cells and detention centers, and intake paperwork. Images are accompanied by detailed captions written by the photographer. The prints measure 17 x 22 inches (image size 16 x 20 inches). As a whole, the collection documents the administration and human context of the 21st century juvenile justice system in the U.S. and Iowa.
In the artist's statement, also included in the collection, Murff writes: "From 2012 to 2015, I worked as a Tracker for Linn County Juvenile Detention and Diversion Services in Cedar Rapids, Iowa. As a Tracker, I provided services to youths who were convicted of crimes, adjudicated, and subsequently ordered to complete probation...Through employing ideas of anonymity, voyeurism, and introspection, 'Corrections' is an examination of youth experience in the system, the role images play in defining someone who is deemed a 'criminal,' and how the concepts of privacy and control may affect their future."
This work received the 2018 ADA Award for Emerging Documentarians. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Electronic monitoring of parolees and probationers -- United States; Juvenile corrections -- Iowa; Juvenile delinquents -- Portraits; Juvenile justice, Administration of -- Iowa; Juvenile probation -- Iowa; Teenagers -- Portraits; Teenagers -- United States -- Social conditions; Iowa -- Photographs; Color photographs; Digital prints; Inkjet prints; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University); Murff, Zora J.
- Corrections, 2013-2015
  - Lucas at 15, 2014; 17 x 22 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11686-P-0001)
  - Omnilink Electronic Monitoring Unit, 2014; 17 x 22 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11686-P-0002)
  - Life, 2013; 22 x 17 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11686-P-0003)
    Scope and Contents
    Scan of the back of an intake assignment worksheet completed by a young man at the Linn County Juvenile Detention Center.
  - Age 17 (Waived), 2015; 22 x 17 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11686-P-0004)
    A digital representation of a young woman who was waived from the juvenile court system to the adult court system after receiving additional charges while on probation.
  - Attempted Murder, Going Armed with Intent, Intimidation with a Dangerous Weapon, Willful Injury Causing Serious Injury, 2014; 17 x 22 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11686-P-0005)
  - Earl at 15 (1:30 pm visit), 17 x 22 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11686-P-0006)
  - Jerome at 15, 2015; 17 x 22 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11686-P-0007)
  - Standard issue: Jumpsuit, 2014; 17 x 22 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11686-P-0008)
  - Jaeshawn at 16, 2014; 17 x 22 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11686-P-0009)
  - Assault on a Peace Officer and Disorderly Conduct, 2013; 17 x 22 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11686-P-0010)
  - Memphis at 16, 2013; 17 x 22 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11686-P-0011)
  - Wendy at 14 and Sheila at 15, 2014; 22 x 17 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11686-P-0012)
  - Criminal Trespassing and Disorderly Conduct, 2013; 17 x 22 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11686-P-0013)
  - My Past Charge, 2013; 22 x 17 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11686-P-0014)
    Scan of a notebook page corresponding to an intake worksheet completed by a you ng woman at the Linn County Juvenile Detention Center.
  - Close to Home, 2014; 17 x 22 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11686-P-0015)
    View of a room at the Foundation 2 Residential Treatment Center.
  - Demetrius and Frank at 15, 2013; 22 x 17 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11686-P-0016)
  - Kenny at 19, 2013; 17 x 22 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11686-P-0017)
  - Robbery, 2015; 17 x 22 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11686-P-0018)
  - Megan at 16, 2014; 22 x 17 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11686-P-0019)
  - Sheila at 16 (Off paper), 2015; 22 x 17 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11686-P-0020)
    A portrait of Sheila on her last day of probation. A colloquialism many of the kids in the system use to reference getting discharged from probation is that they are, "off paper."
  - Earl's bed (Hickory Pod), 2015; 17 x 22 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11686-P-0021)
    A view of a bed in a cell at the Linn County Juvenile Detention Center.
  - Age 19 (Reoffended as an adult), 2015; 22 x 17 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11686-P-0022)
    A digital representation of a man who was discharged from probation at age 18 and then convicted of a crime as an adult.
  - My goals, 2013; 22 x 17 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11686-P-0023)
    Scan of a notebook page corresponding to an assignment worksheet completed by a young man at the Linn County Juvenile Detention Center.
  - Dillon at 18 (Off paper), 2015; 22 x 17 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11686-P-0024)
    A portrait of Dillon on his last day of probation.
  - Entrance/Exit, 2015; 17 x 22 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11686-P-0025)
    A view of the intake entrance/exit at the Linn County Juvenile Detention Center.